Guide to the Griffith J. Davis photographs and films, 1946-1991 RL.00292
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Griffith J. Davis photographs and films
1946-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Davis, Griffith J., 1923-1993
RL.00292
6 Linear Feet 7 boxes; 1 film reel container
Griff Davis (1923-1993) was a photojournalist, diplomat, and film maker from Atlanta, Georgia. The collection contains photographic materials and papers related to three photo essays illustrated by Davis: one on African American writer Langston Hughes; another on artists Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston; and one on the Palmer Memorial Institute, a private preparatory school for African Americans in Sedalia, N.C. Films in the collection were taken by Davis and include two home movies and six color and black-and-white 16mm films documenting people, politics, and agricultural life in Liberia during William Tubman's presidency in the early 1950s. Completing the collection is a photo album, "Progress in Liberia, Nov. 1949-Feb. 1950," containing twenty large black-and-white photographs, assembled to promote a partnership between the government of Liberia and the Liberia Mining Company. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical Note: Griff Davis (1923-1993)
Griffith J. Davis, known as "Griff," was born in Atlanta, Georgia on April 18, 1923. He was introduced to photography during high school. After serving in World War II, Davis returned to Atlanta where his photojournalism career flourished as he worked while at Morehouse College for the Atlanta Daily World, Time, and Ebony, who authorized him to do a photojournalism spread on his sister's high school, the Palmer Memorial Institute, a private boarding school in North Carolina.
Griff Davis' journalistic career introduced him to many political and cultural players of the time, including Langston Hughes, who was one of his earliest mentors. Davis received his M.A. in journalism from Columbia in 1949, the only Black student in the program. As a journalist for the Black Star photo agency, New York Times, Ebony, and many other publications, Davis traveled in the United States, Africa, and Europe during the forties and fifties. In 1952 the Republic of Liberia sponsored Davis' one-man show "Liberia, 1952," at the American Museum of Natural History, and in the years that followed he produced three documentary films, including one narrated by the then-unknown actor Sidney Poitier.
In 1952 Davis joined the U.S. Foreign Service, spending most of his time advancing Truman's Point Four program for foreign aid (later USAID), chiefly in Liberia. He also served in Tunisia and Nigeria, and retired in 1985. In 1993, Morehouse College awarded Davis the Bennie Trailblazer Award, named for his former mentor and president of Morehouse, Benjamin Mays, for personal and professional achievements. Griff Davis passed away in 1993 in Atlanta, Georgia at the age of 70.
[Adapted from Wikipedia website biography and "Still Here: The Griffith J. Davis Photographs and Archive in Context," University of South Florida exhibit website, introduction by Dorothy Davis, viewed July 1, 2021]
Biographical Note: Charles Alston (1907-1977)
Charles Alston was an African American painter, sculptor, illustrator, muralist and teacher based in the New York City neighborhood of Harlem. He was active in the Harlem Renaissance. Alston was born in 1907 in Charlotte, N.C. His father had been born into slavery in 1851 in Pittsboro, North Carolina. After the Civil War, Alston gained an education and graduated from St. Augustine's College in Raleigh. Through marriage, he became close to artist Romare Bearden and his family. Alston designed and painted murals at the Harlem Hospital and the Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Building. He passed away in 1977.
[Source: Adapted from Wikipedia website biography, viewed July 1, 2021]
Biographical Note: Langston Hughes (1902-1967)
Langston Hughes (1902-1967), who claimed Paul Lawrence Dunbar, Carl Sandburg, and Walt Whitman as his primary influences, is particularly known for his insightful portrayals of Black life in America from the 1920s through the 1960s. Hughes wrote novels, short stories, plays, and poetry, and is also known for his engagement with the world of jazz and the influence it had on his writing, as in his book-length poem "Montage of a Dream Deferred" (Holt, 1951). His life and work were enormously important in shaping the artistic contributions of the 1920s Harlem Renaissance.
[Source: Adapted from Wikipedia website biography, viewed July 1, 2021]
Biographical Note: Hale Woodruff (1900-1980)
Hale Aspacio Woodruff (1900-1980) was an American-born painter, draftsman, printer, and educator who is probably best known for his murals, especially the Amistad Mutiny Murals (1939) at the Savery Library at Talladega College in Alabama. Woodruff studied in France from 1927 to 1931, and was greatly influenced by African art and cubism. However, upon his return to the United States he concentrated on social issues, including scenes of Southern poverty and depictions of lynchings.
[Source: Adapted from Wikipedia website entry, viewed July 1, 2021]
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats. Digital viewing files for all still image negatives are available directly through this collection guide. Moving image films are closed to general use; viewing copies are available. Contact Research Services for more information.
Provenance
The Griffith J. Davis photographs and films were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts and a purchase from 1999 to 2011.
Related Materials
Griffith Davis Photograph Collection, Moorland-Spingarn Research Center, Howard University.
Collection Overview
The Griffith J. Davis Photographs and Films collection dates from 1949-1991 and comprises two main series: films and a photo album made in the 1950s in Liberia and documenting life there during part of William V. Tubman's presidency; and photographs, contact prints, hundreds of digitized nitrate and safety negatives, and related papers documenting three photo-essays, one on African American author Langston Hughes; another on artists Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston; and one on the Palmer Memorial Institute, a private junior and senior high school for African Americans in Sedalia, N.C. The digitized negatives are also available through the Duke Libraries Digital Collections website.
Photographic materials include two sheets of photographic contact prints taken by Davis when he visited Methodist missionaries Mr. and Mrs. George Way Harley in Ganta, Liberia. Subjects include African masks and the Ganta Mission. A letter written by Davis describes his visit with the Harleys.
Other Griff Davis images in the collection are found in an album entitled "Progress in Liberia, November 1949 - February 1950," containing a map of Liberia and twenty large black-and-white gelatin silver prints with typed captions. Subjects feature Liberian landscapes, construction projects, bridges, railroads, and port scenes, with some images featuring native Liberian workers. The album was assembled to promote the partnership with the Liberian government and the Liberia Mining Company; in the first image, President Tubman is signing a contract with mining officials.
The audiovisual components include two home movies taken in Monrovia, and six color and black-and-white films taken in Liberia by Davis in the 1950s during William V.S. Tubman's presidency. Davis was asked by Tubman to document modern life in Liberia in 1952. In 1956 and 1957 he made films while stationed in Liberia with the United States technical assistance mission and the Liberian Ministry of Information and Broadcasting. Films depict a wide range of subjects, activities and events, including the country's people, industry, leaders, and rural life. Titles include Pepper Bird Land (1952), Liberia 1956 Presidential Inauguration of William V. S. Tubman & William R. Tolbert, President and the Press Exhibit (1956), Gold Coast Prime Minister Kwame Nkrumah Visits Liberia (1953), Progress Through Cooperation (1957), home movie Coketails for Dorothy, Monrovia Children's Birthday Party (1956), and Night Village Dancing in Liberia (1956).
African American artists; African American authors; African American diplomats; African American journalists; African American photographers -- Georgia; African American poets; African American high school students -- Photographs; African American schools -- North Carolina -- Photographs; African Americans -- Education (Secondary) -- North Carolina; Documentary Photography -- United States; Liberia -- Economic conditions; Liberia -- History -- 1944-1971; United States -- Foreign relations -- Liberia; Cellulose nitrate film; Contact prints; DVDs; Film; Moving images; Negatives (photographs); Photograph albums; Videocassettes; Palmer Memorial Institute (Sedalia, N.C.); Woodruff, Hale, 1900-1980; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Davis, Griffith J., 1923-1993; Alston, Charles Henry, 1907-1977; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Tubman, William V. S., 1895-1971
- Photographs and papers, 1946-1991; 1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes
  - Correspondence and information about Griff Davis (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of articles and other publications (Box 1)
  - Information folder on Langston Hughes (Box 1)
  - Information folder on Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston, mural artists (Box 1)
  - Contact sheets and photographs, 1946-circa 1950 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This series consists chiefly of contact sheets created by Davis from his nitrate and safety film negatives, also found in this collection. The original negative numbers are marked next to each image on the contact sheet, and in a few cases, there are captions.
    Not all of the 342 negatives in the collection are represented on these contact sheets; however, all of the negatives have been digitally scanned and are available to view through the Scanned Negatives series in this collection guide.
    A few gelatin silver prints are included in the contact sheet folders, left as they were originally filed.
  - Photograph album: "Progress in Liberia, Nov. 1949-Feb. 1950", circa 1950 (Box 6)
    This album was created with photographs by Griff Davis to promote a partnership between the government of Liberia and Liberia Mining Company. It contains 20 black-and-white prints, measuring approximately 10 1/4 x 12 1/4 inches, and each print includes a typed caption.
- Scanned still image negatives, 1946-1949; 342 items 2 boxes
  The 342 original safety and nitrate cellulose film negatives in this collection were taken by photojournalist Griff Davis for use in three publication projects. They are almost all black-and-white.
  Almost a third of the images, 108 negatives, derive from a photo-essay in Ebony magazine on African American author and New York resident Langston Hughes. Another 124 images document African American student life at the Palmer Memorial Institute preparatory school in Sedalia, N.C., also published in Ebony. Finally, 110 images document African American artists and mural painters Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston at work in their studio on a mural for the Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company. There are also a dozen color photographs of Alston's modernist paintings and a sculpture.
  All of the negatives were digitally scanned for preservation purposes by library staff; the digital files are viewable through links in this collection guide, or through the Duke University Libraries Digital Collections website.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats. Digital viewing files for all negative images are available through this collection guide.
  Related Materials
  Most of the images in this negatives series are found on contact sheets in the Photographs and Papers series; related materials in that same series include copies of parts of the published articles, correspondence, and other items.
  - Palmer Memorial Institute, Sedalia, North Carolina, 1946-1947; 124 items
    Historical Note
    The founder of Palmer Memorial Institute, Charlotte Hawkins Brown (1883–1961) was born in Henderson, North Carolina, and raised and educated in Massachusetts. Brown named the Alice Freeman Palmer Memorial Institute (PMI) in Sedalia, North Carolina, after her mentor and benefactor, the second woman president of Wellesley College. Brown raised funds to expand campus facilities and worked to strengthen PMI's artistic and scholarly offerings, and through her efforts, the school evolved from an agricultural and manual training facility to a fully accredited, nationally recognized African American preparatory school for junior and senior high school students. In 1987 the Charlotte Hawkins Brown Museum opened on the PMI grounds as North Carolina's first African American state historic site.
    [Source: Adapted from the National Park Service website on a traveling exhibition of Griff Davis photographs of PMI, viewed July 1, 2021]
    The Palmer Memorial Institute (PMI) was an African American preparatory school for junior and senior students, and was attended by more than 1,000 students from 1902 until it closed in 1971. In 1946 and 1947, Griff Davis visited the school, documenting daily student life at PMI for a 1947 photo-essay in Ebony magazine. A copy of this article is in the Photographs and Papers series.
    The images show students in class and enjoying extra-curricular programs and recreation; school administrators, including President and founder Charlotte Hawkins Brown; and teachers.
    Positive scans of the negative images are available for viewing through the links with each entry.
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-1 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0001)
      Palmer Memorial Institute.
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-2A (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0002)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-2B (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0003)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-3A (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0004)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-3B (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0005)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-4 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0006)
    - At lunchtime, Henri sings grace which is custom for each meal. Before supper, hymn is sung. Students serve as waiters for two-week periods. Dining etiquette is strictly observed and anyone violating rules eats alone., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-5 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0007)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine (photocopy in collection folder).
    - Writing for student newspaper, Henri does fashion notes. "Sedalia Sentinel" is a monthly mimeographed sheet. Henri hopes to become a writer, favors English as a subject. She has made dean's honor list every semester., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-6 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0008)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-7 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0009)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-8 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0010)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same shot as PMI-9. "Favorite hangout on campus is co-op Tea Room which takes up recess time and student allowances (average $10 monthly)."
    - Favorite hangout on campus is co-op Tea Room which takes up recess time and student allowances (average $10 monthly). Henri's is $13, including $4 from campus job. Girls are not allowed in Tea Room after supper., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-9 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0011)
    - Dovey M. Davis, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-10 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0012)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from Davis' contact sheet.
    - Daily personal contact with each student is a must in Dr. Charlotte Hawkins Brown's education formula, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-11 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0013)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine. The rest of the caption reads, "In her office (above) she talks over student affairs with senior class president Edward Clark of New York. Each morning at 8:30 chapel service (below) she addresses student body, limited to enrollment of 240."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-12 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0014)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-13 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0015)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-14 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0016)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-15 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0017)
    - Walking gracefully is one of the key lessons in Palmer "charm class." Here senior Florence Edmonds, Washington, D.C., demonstrates right technique with book on head., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-16 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0018)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine (photocopy in collection folder). The rest of the caption reads, "Palmer teaches proper manners but does not regard itself as a 'sissy school.' For 35 vacancies this coming school year, more than 600 applications have been received."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-17 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0019)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-18 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0020)
    - Waltz Routine is performed by seniors during intermission. Boys are not required to dress formally although most girls wear formals., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-19 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0021)
    - Modern dance class (Henri at right) rehearses original "Let My People Go", 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-20 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0022)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine. The rest of the caption reads, "Class is required for junior and senior girls. On Fridays all Palmer girls dress uniformly in navy blue or black skirts and white blouses with black neckerchiefs. All boys wear ties. Costume is for special chapel service."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-21 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0023)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same setting as PMI-20.
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-22 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0024)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-23 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0025)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-24 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0026)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-25 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0027)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same setting as PMI-26. "Whist game at campus cottage of Dean Donald Montague is big social occasion."
    - Whist game at campus cottage of Dean Donald Montague is big social occasion, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-26 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0028)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine (photocopy in collection folder). Remainder of caption reads, "Gambling is prohibited along with games like poker. Men are not permitted to smoke on campus although teachers may smoke in their homes."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-27 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0029)
    - Dovey M. Davis, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-28 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0030)
    - Dovey M. Davis, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-29 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0031)
    - J. Warrick?, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-30 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0032)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title, including question mark, transcribed from Davis' contact sheet.
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-31 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0033)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-32 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0034)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same shot as PMI-33. "Music lessons are taken by every PMI student. Henri has played piano since 7, here rehearses for concert with violinist Victor Vick."
    - Music lessons are taken by every PMI student. Henri has played piano since 7, here rehearses for concert with violinist Victor Vick., 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-33 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0035)
    - Mother's visit to campus is treat for Henri, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-34 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0036)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine (photocopy in collection folder). Rest of caption reads, "Mrs. Juanita Peyton drove down from home in Newport New, Va., to attend YWCA confab in Greensboro, N.C., stopped off on way. Frequent visiting by parents in discouraged. Those living nearby are asked to come no more than three or four times a year."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-35 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0037)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same setting as PMI-34. "Mother's visit to campus is treat for Henri."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-36 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0038)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same shot as PMI-34. "Mother's visit to campus is treat for Henri."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-37 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0039)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-38 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0040)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-39 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0041)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-40 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0042)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-41 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0043)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-42 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0044)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-43 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0045)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-44 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0046)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-45 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0047)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-46 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0048)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Image is not present in contact sheets.
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-47 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0049)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-48 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0050)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-49 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0051)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Same shot as PMI-50. "Singing with PMI chorus, Henri (second row, third from right) wears surplice."
    - Singing with PMI chorus, Henri (second row, third from right) wears surplice, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-50 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0052)
      Palmer Memorial Institute. Title transcribed from caption in Ebony magazine (photocopy in collection folder). Rest of caption reads, "Sedalia Singers have raised voices, money and praise for Palmer at White House, New York's Town Hall and Boston's Symphony Hall. All students must learn Hallelujah Chorus from Messiah for each commencement."
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-51 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0053)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-52 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0054)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-53 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0055)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-54 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0056)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-55 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0057)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-56 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0058)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-57 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0059)
    - No known title, 1946-1947; Original identifier: PMI-58 (Box 2, Image RL.00292-N-0060)